Konvitz, Milton R. American Ideals Lectures Audio-Visual Materials /4039 AV
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Milton R. Konvitz American Ideals Lectures Audio-Visual Materials
1973- 1974
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Konvitz, Milton R.
/4039 AV
10.56 cubic feet
10.6 linear ft.
Audiocassettes, compact discs, sound recordings, audiovisual materials.
Collection of Milton Konvitz's lectures from January, February, March and April of 1973.
6115214
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183> kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff, August 15, 2013
EAD encoding:
Randall Miles, September 23, 2016
Biographical / Historical
March 12, 1908-September 5, 2003 Milton Konvitz, a Cornell University faculty member and authority on constitutional and labor law, and civil and human rights, died Sept. 5 at the age of 95. Konvitz was a founding faculty member in the School of Industrial and Labor Relations from 1946 until his retirement in 1973. He was also a professor in Cornell's Law School. Konvitz is perhaps best known for his American Ideals course, which he taught to more than 8,000 students over the course of his career, never giving the same lecture twice. "I saw the U.S. Constitution as it has been interpreted as a magnificent depository of our ideals, both individual and social," he said. His course exposed students to the great intellectual thinkers and philosophers throughout history whose writings had shaped those ideals. They included Sophocles, whose play Antigone is Cornell's New Student Reading Project this year. One student he influenced was U.S. Supreme Court Justice Ruth Bader Ginsburg, Cornell Class of 1954, who considers him a mentor. At Cornell Konvitz also was a founder of the university's Department of Near Eastern Studies and Program of Jewish Studies. "I felt it was essential for a college interested in the humanities not to leave out Hebrew language and literature," he said. "And the knowledge of Jewish history, which began 4,000 years ago and has contributed to civilization no less than Greek, Roman or English history, is important to today's students-Jewish and non-Jewish." He often hosted students at his Ithaca home and helped start the first Kosher dining option at Cornell, Young Israel House. In addition, for nearly 30 years he directed the Liberian Codification Project, which drew up the official body of statutory laws that is still in force in the Republic of Liberia today, despite the current political upheaval there. Konvitz also edited the opinions of Liberia's Supreme Court and received the Grand Band of the Order of the Star of Africa, the highest award given to foreigners, as well as an honorary degree from the University of Liberia, one of seven honorary degrees he received in his lifetime. Active as a scholar and writer until his death, he wrote books and articles on American constitutional law that won him wide recognition and were cited in U.S. Supreme Court opinions. Among his nine books is Fundamental Liberties of a Free People: Religion, Speech, Press, Assembly, which was republished earlier this year with an expanded introduction by him that is strongly critical of the Rehnquist Supreme Court. Other books include A Century of Civil Rights (1983) and Judaism and Human Rights (2nd ed. 2001). He also edited a dozen volumes, including two on American philosopher Ralph Waldo Emerson, whose thinking shaped his views. One Emersonian idea he absorbed was that readers give life to books, which Konvitz recast as follows: "It is in their hearing that students bring life to the words, the thoughts, the teacher." Konvitz was born in Safed, Palestine (now Israel ), in 1908, the son of a rabbi. He immigrated to the United States in 1915 and became a naturalized citizen in 1926. He received a bachelor's degree in 1929 and a law degree in 1930, both from New York University, and a Ph.D. in philosophy from Cornell in 1933. Before joining Cornell's faculty, he was one of three assistant general counsels to Thurgood Marshall at the NAACP Legal Defense Fund for three years. He is survived by his wife, Mary, of Oakhurst, N.J.; a brother, Phillip, of Elberon, N.J.; a son and daughter-in- law, Josef and Isa, of Paris, France; and two grandsons, Eli and Ezra. Josef Konvitz, who grew up in Ithaca, is now an official at the Organization for Economic Co-operation and Development.
Scope and Contents
Collection of Milton Konvitz's lectures from January, February, March and April of 1973.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: /3033: Milton R. Konvitz Liberian Project Files /4039: Milton R. Konvitz Papers /4039 a: Milton R. Konvitz Papers Guide (Volume 1). Laser Copy /4039 B: Milton R. Konvitz Additional Papers /4039 L: Milton R. Konvitz Liberian Codification Project /4085: Milton R. Konvitz Additional Papers /4220m: Milton Konvitz Additional Papers /4289 AV: ILR School Alumni Affairs and Development Audio-Visual Materials /4297: ILR School Biography Files 6047: Archives Information File
United States -- Social conditions; United States -- Politics and government; Konvitz, Milton R.(Milton Ridvas), 1908-2003.
6115214
- Jan. 22, 1973 - Circ. Copy (Box 1)
- Jan. 24, 1973 - Circ. Copy (Box 2)
- Jan. 26, 1973 - Circ. Copy (Box 3)
- Jan. 29, 1973 - Circ. Copy (Box 4)
- Jan. 31, 1973 - Circ. Copy (Box 5)
- Feb. 2, 1973 - Circ. Copy (Box 6)
- Feb. 5, 1973 - Circ. Copy (Box 7)
- Feb. 7, 1973 - Circ. Copy (Box 8)
- Feb. 9, 1973 - Circ. Copy (Box 9)
- Feb. 12, 1973 - Circ. Copy (Box 10)
- Feb. 16, 1973 - Circ. Copy (Box 11)
- Feb. 19, 1973 - Circ. Copy (Box 12)
- Feb. 21, 1973 - Circ. Copy (Box 13)
- Feb. 23, 1973 - Circ. Copy (Box 14)
- Feb. 26, 1973 - Circ. Copy (Box 15)
- Feb. 28, 1973 - Circ. Copy (Box 16)
- Mar. 2, 1973 - Circ. Copy (Box 17)
- Mar. 4, 1973 - Circ. Copy (Box 18)
- Mar. 5, 1973 - Circ. Copy (Box 19)
- Mar. 9, 1973 - Circ. Copy (Box 20)
- Mar. 12, 1973 - Circ. Copy (Box 21)
- Mar. 14, 1973 - Circ. Copy (Box 22)
- Mar. 16, 1973 - Circ. Copy (Box 23)
- Mar. 26, 1973 - Circ. Copy (Box 24)
- Mar. 28, 1973 - Circ. Copy (Box 25)
- Mar. 30, 1973 - Circ. Copy (Box 26)
- Apr. 9, 1973 - Circ. Copy (Box 27)
- Apr. 9, 1973 (Box 28)
- Apr. 13, 1973 - Circ. Copy (Box 29)
- Apr. 16, 1973 - Circ. Copy (Box 30)
- Apr. 18, 1973 - Circ. Copy (Box 31)
- Apr. 20, 1973 - Circ. Copy (Box 32)
- Apr. 25, 1973 - Circ. Copy (Box 33)
- Apr. 27, 1973 - Circ. Copy (Box 34)
- Apr. 30, 1973 - Circ. Copy (Box 35)
- Apr. 2001 - New York City - Dupl. Master (Box 36)
- Series 1, Discs 1-3, MP3 Conversions - Dupl. Master (Box 37)
- Jan. 22, 1973 - Dupl. Master (Box 38)
- Jan. 24, 1973 - Dupl. Master (Box 39)
- Jan. 26, 1973 - Dupl. Master (Box 40)
- Jan. 29, 1973 - Dupl. Master (Box 41)
- Jan. 31, 1973 - Dupl. Master (Box 42)
- Feb. 2, 1973 - Dupl. Master (Box 43)
- Feb. 5, 1973 - Dupl. Master (Box 44)
- Feb. 7, 1973 - Dupl. Master (Box 45)
- Feb. 9, 1973 - Dupl. Master (Box 46)
- Feb. 12, 1973 - Dupl. Master (Box 47)
- Feb. 16, 1973 - Dupl. Master (Box 48)
- Feb. 19, 1973 - Dupl. Master (Box 49)
- Feb. 21, 1973 - Dupl. Master (Box 50)
- Feb. 23, 1973 - Dupl. Master (Box 51)
- Feb. 26, 1973 - Dupl. Master (Box 52)
- Feb. 28, 1973 - Dupl. Master (Box 53)
- Mar. 2, 1973 - Dupl. Master (Box 54)
- Mar. 4, 1973 - Dupl. Master (Box 55)
- Mar. 5, 1973 - Dupl. Master (Box 56)
- Mar. 9, 1973 - Dupl. Master (Box 57)
- Mat. 12, 1973 - Dupl. Master (Box 58)
- Mar. 14, 1973 - Dupl. Master (Box 59)
- Mar. 16, 1973 - Dupl. Master (Box 60)
- Mar. 26, 1973 - Dupl. Master (Box 61)
- Mar. 28, 1973 - Dupl. Master (Box 62)
- Mar. 30, 1973 - Dupl. Master (Box 63)
- Apr. 6, 1973 - Dupl. Master (Box 64)
- Apr. 9, 1973 - Dupl. Master (Box 65)
- Apr. 13, 1973 - Dupl. Master (Box 66)
- Apr. 16, 1973 - Dupl. Master (Box 67)
- Apr. 18, 1973 - Dupl. Master (Box 68)
- Apr. 20, 1973 - Dupl. Master (Box 69)
- Apr. 25, 1973 - Dupl. Master (Box 70)
- Apr. 27, 1973 - Dupl. Master (Box 71)
- Apr. 30, 1973 - Dupl. Master (Box 72)
- Series 1, Discs 1-3 MP3 Conversions - Dupl. Master (Box 73)
- Test Disc #2 MP3 Conversions - Dupl. Master (Box 74)
- Extra ILR Test #2 - Dupl. Master (Box 75)
- This box is in the Annex (Box 76)
- Milton Konvitz interviewed on his papers (Box 77)
- Konvitz and Applegate - 12/17/1981 (Box 78)
- 1973-1974 Cassettes (Box 79)
  Scope and Contents
  63 - 1973 cassettes; 99-1974 cassettes and 4 unlabeled - housed in Annex